<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A notable and comfortable exposition, vpon the fourth of Mathevv; concerning the tentations of Christ preached in S.Peters Church, in Oxenford; By Thomas Bentham, fellovv ov Magdalin Colledge and afterwards Vyshop of Liechfeeld and Coventrie.</title>
            <author>Bentham, Thomas, 1513-1579.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1583</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 750 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1891</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111929</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847189</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847189</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12212</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08599)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12212)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 173:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A notable and comfortable exposition, vpon the fourth of Mathevv; concerning the tentations of Christ preached in S.Peters Church, in Oxenford; By Thomas Bentham, fellovv ov Magdalin Colledge and afterwards Vyshop of Liechfeeld and Coventrie.</title>
                  <author>Bentham, Thomas, 1513-1579.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Walde-graue, dwelling in Foster-Lane, ouer against Goldsmiths Hall,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1583?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Around title page ornament: God is my defender.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A godly sermon of M.Benthams vpon the tentations of Christ.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original at the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12212:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12212:1"/>
            <p>¶ A notable and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable expoſition, vpon the FOVRTH OF MATHEVV<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> CONCER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ations of Christ, Preac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> in S. Peters Church, in Oxenford<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>By Thomas Ben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n Colledge and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and COVENTRIE.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of swan</figDesc>
               <head>GOD IS MY DEFENDER</head>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Printed by Robert <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, dwelling in Foſter-Lane, ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>ſt Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Hall.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12212:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12212:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Math. 4. 1. 2. 3. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11.</bibl>
               <q>Then Ieſus was lead a way of the Spirite into the Wilderneſſe, to be tempted of the Deuil. &amp;c.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He miſery of man (dearely bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ued in our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſte) may the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore plainely and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anifeſtly appeare onto vs, if we dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently conſider, in what ſtate, digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and honour man was, before the olde malicious, and wicked Serpent, with his ſubtle ſuggeſtions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, had tempted, perſwaded, and ouercommed him. And againe, if af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his ouerthrow wee conſider, in what miſerable calamitie, captiuity, ſlauerie, and ſeruile bondage, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Adam</hi> him ſelfe, but alſo all his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, is enthralled and impryſoned with him. And againe if we marke, how weake, feeble, and impotent, ſince
<pb facs="tcp:12212:3"/> that time, man is in all knowledge, godlineſſe, and obedience: and how ſtrong, ſaucie, malapert, and readie the aduerſarie is, to detain and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue him in ignorance, idolatrie, diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and rebellion againſt God, and his holy word. Which vnſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table miſeries, if they be deeply conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and duely weighed in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of our conſciences, with a confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the former ſtate, which was happy, bleſſed, &amp; immortall, with the preſent ſtate, which is ſinfull, accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and damnable: may eaſily make vs to perceiue, that there is ſome great cauſe, why our felicity, is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into miſerie, our bleſſedneſſe, into curſedneſſe, our obedience, into rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, immortallitie into corruption: and to be ſhort, life, into death: and not this onely, but alſo that the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my hath been ſtrong and able inough to keepe and hold man without hope of recouerie, in theſe foreſayd diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes The cauſe whereof, the ignorant and blind worldlings, impute and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the inconſtancie of fortune,
<pb facs="tcp:12212:3"/> and as they terme them, infortunate and vnlucky chaunces, where as the holy word of God declareth vnto vs, that all theſe miſeries and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, are the fearefull puniſhmentes and horrible plagues of God againſt ſinne, as a iuſt reward and ſtipend of the ſame. Wherefore the godly, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing thorough theſe continual and daily plagues, which we ſuffer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gret diſpleaſure &amp; indignation of God to be ſo ſore ſtirred and encenſed againſt man for his ſin, and that they are not able to ſtand in his preſence, with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation and gronings, ſeeke for that helpe, aid, and ſuccour, againſte all ſtormie Tempeſtes, which they know to be ſet forth and appointed in Gods holy worde: truſting either by thoſe meanes to come into Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour again or elſe by no other means poſſible. And theſe means as they are ſet forth in diuers and ſundry places of ſcripture: ſo are they in no place more to our comfort and conſolation, then in this preſent goſpel, red in the holy Church as this day. Wherein is
<pb facs="tcp:12212:4"/> conteined, a mighty, triumphant, and glorious victory of our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte, gotten to all Chriſtian and faithfull beleeuers ouer that trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, auncient, and expert tempter ſathan, the original and curſed cauſe, of all theſe wretched intollerable mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries. Who, at the beginning, gaue man ſuch an ouerthrow, that from thence to this conſlict, there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more manifeſt hope of riſing, nor a more euident ſigne of victory. For here is declared vnto vs. that the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and malicious worker of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which hath ſo long pinched at our heele and bitten vs by the feete, according to Gods promiſe, hath now ſuch a ſoyle, that he is not onely tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den<note place="margin">Gen. 3. 15.</note> vnderfoote, but is in his heade ſo wounded, bruiſed and cruſhed in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by that moſt bleſſed ſeede of the woman, betweene whome there hath been ſo long continuall enimity, that there is on his part no hope of helpe, no recouery of health, bee he neuer ſo ſtrong and ſtoute, be he neuer ſo craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and deceitful. If we, eſpecially that
<pb facs="tcp:12212:4"/> meane to be true ſouldiers to our cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, will take vpon vs the armour of God, that S. <hi>Paul</hi> willeth vs to put<note place="margin">Eph. 6. 11.</note> on, we may nowe (God be thanked) not onely withſtand him, and bouldly fight with him, but alſo euen van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh him, and trample him vnder our feet. For he, which did ouerthrow now is ouerthrowne, the deceiuer is caught in his own ſnare. the Captain is become captiue, the ruler of the world. the Prince of darkenes, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all lying, whome man coulde not withſtand, nor the world ſubdue, he being Lord thereof, with a worde rebuked &amp; reiected, is vtterly ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp; clean put to flight. We need not therfore be afraid to fight, ſeeing our captaine is a conqueror, &amp; our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conquered, our captaine ſtrong, our enimie weake, our Captaine to ſtande, our enimie to flée, our Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to haue praiſe and glory, our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy ſhame and reproch: but the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie of Chriſt may bee an encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of vs to fight, and his valiant conqueſt an example for vs to ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:12212:5"/> ſtoutly againſt our enemie. And is not here (dearely beloued) great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and conſolation for all them, that are afraid of the deuil? Therefore I note it the more diligently, becauſe that when we are tempted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as our ſauiour Chriſt was, we giue not place daſtardly to our aduerſary who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God ſuffereth to tempt, partlie, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we may learn to know y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> vertue of our armor which we haue put on: partlie alſo, that we may learne to fight and bee warriours when wee ſhall be tried. By temptation a man is tried, as gould is tried in a furnace: &amp; by that means a man ſhal not waxe proude, hauing his enemy alwaies readie to abate his courage, &amp; to trie his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. It is no ſmall comfort to haue this victorie ſet before our eies, as it is moſt plainly written in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente Goſpell, by the Euangeliſt. But leaſte I ſhoulde confounde the victory, I wil orderly ſpeake of euery part by it ſelfe, if time wil ſuffer me, and the ſpirit of God giue me vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. <hi>Let vs pray &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12212:5"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Math. 4. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>
                     <note place="margin">Text.</note> Then Ieſus was lead away of the Spirite into the Wilderneſſe, to be tempted of the Deuil. &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THe firſt worde in this goſpel, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs to pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſe a part of the Chapter going afore: becauſe it is a conſeqent following former act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and deedes. In which Chapiter, the euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt S <hi>Mathew,</hi> hath ſet downe the office and miniſterye of S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the baptiſt, how he teſtified of Chriſt, and prepared the way for the people <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> ſo much as was neceſſarye for his purpoſe, that entended to write and ſet forth Chriſt his acts, life, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. Becauſe therfore that now the order of the hiſtory, and courſe of things do ſo require, he beginneth to write what Chriſt did after his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, &amp; moſt heauenly commenceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which was immediatly going before in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> latter end of the third chapter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For whereas Chriſt alwaies before his baptiſme, was obedient vnto <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> &amp; <hi>Mary,</hi> occupied &amp; exerciſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in their laboures and buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes:
<pb facs="tcp:12212:6"/> yet now by baptiſme altered, as it were, into a new man, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated vnto God his Father, whoſe will he came to fulfill, returned not thither whence he came, to become ſuche an one as hee was before, as in other ſolemne Feaſtes and times at <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ruſalem</hi> hee was wont, but [<hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately</hi>] after his Baptiſme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as S. <hi>Mark</hi> termeth that, which this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt calleth [<hi>then,</hi>] hee was led of the holy ghoſt into the deſart to bee voyd of company and conuerſation of men, and to liue with beaſtes, where was ſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſity and lack of things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the ſuſtentation of mans life, that the Deuil might the rather take occaſion to tempt him, being in a place where he wanted reliefe, then where hee had plentye of all thinges, For if Chriſt had beene in the Citye <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> or in other villages, where victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als might haue beene come by conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently and in time, the deuil woulde not then ſo boldly haue enterpriſed to bring him ſtones to make breade: which had beene folly and in vayne,
<pb facs="tcp:12212:6"/> when bread had beene at hande. But becauſe there was nothing in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart for man to eat, there the tempter took occaſion to tempt &amp; to try Chriſt. Here, in that the Euangeliſt ſaith, <hi>Then was Ieſus lead of the ſpirit,</hi> that is, immediatly after his baptiſme, I note as a fruitfull leſſon, that they which are appoynted of God to any high office or miniſtery<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are, or ought to be clean altered and changed from that they haue beene before, as was heere our Sauiour Chriſt. Who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his baptiſme, liued and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ordinarily, as the common ſort of men did, but after he was baptiſed, as he altered his liuing, ſo did he his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, which before was bodilye exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, but nowe was all ſpirituall and heauenly, in praying, faſting, and preaching S. <hi>Paule</hi> teacheth vs the like leſſon, that after we be baptiſed, we are no more as we were. He ſaith:<note place="margin">Rom. 6. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Remember ye not, that we all which are baptiſed in the name of Ieſus Christ, are baptiſed with him to dye? We are buried with him by baptiſme for to dye, that
<pb facs="tcp:12212:7"/> lyke as Christ was raiſed vp from death by the glory of the father: euen ſo we alſo ſhould walke in a new life.</hi> He ſayth we ſhould now, after our baptiſme walk in a new life, not in that life we were in before. For now being baptiſed in<note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> Chriſt, we haue put on Chriſt, as he writeth to the <hi>Galatians:</hi> and all they which are called to the ſtate of grace, by baptiſm, put of the olde man, and put on the new, and that is the true altering and chaunging of our life. Yet, there is an other altering and chaun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of life, in all them that are called to any high office. As, <hi>Moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> beeing called of God to deliuer his people from the tyrannie of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 3. &amp;. 4.</note> and receiuing his office with ſignes &amp; miracles from God: neither retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to his Father in lawes ſheepe, which he was keeping when he was called, nor liued as he was wont, but in the name of the Lorde tooke vpon him to deliuer his people, and ſafely conduct them thorough the Red ſea, and was their paſtour and gouernor, after that in the Wilderneſſe, Forty
<pb facs="tcp:12212:7"/> yeares. King <hi>Dauid</hi> alſo the yongeſt<note place="margin">1. Sam. 16.</note> ſonne of his Father <hi>Iſay,</hi> called from his fathers flock, and annoynted king by <hi>Samuell,</hi> yet left his flocke, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed his vocation. Theſe and ſuch like examples doe well declare, that men called to an high office or mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, muſt be altered from that they were, and be conformed in life and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation to their miniſterie. Which thing, I beſéech you all to doe, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer God, of his infinite goodneſſe and mercye, calleth you to any high ſtate or condition of office or miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. For you ought of very duety and conſcience to alter your life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, that it may be agreing and anſwearable to your office, that your office may be furniſhed and honored, rather with a Godly life, then defaced and ſtayned with a corrupt conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But eſpecially you my brethren which are called of God to the digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Prieſthood, to bee miniſters of his ſecrets, Stewards of his hoſhold, Preachers of his moſte holy worde, Teachers of his people that liue in
<pb facs="tcp:12212:8"/> blindnes and ignoraunce, Paſtors of his ſheepe, watchmen ouer his flocke, bought with Chriſte his precious bloud. I beſeech and exhort you in the tender mercy of God, to conſider your condition, to looke to your office &amp; du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to remember your vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to haue an eye to your conſcience, to which I ſpeak, not to your eares. Now, you are not of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, wherfore your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation muſt bee heauenly: you are conſecrated to God, your liuing muſt be godly. Note wel what S. <hi>Paul</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to <hi>Timothie: No man that warr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th, entangleth him ſelfe with worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and that becauſe he woulde pleaſe him, that hath choſen him to be a ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi> God hath choſen you for his chiefe ſouldiers, ſeek therfore to pleaſe him, and entangle not your ſelues with worldly cares and buſineſſe. But alas what ſhoulde I exhort, where exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation will take no place, or deſire, where intreatie will not ſerue? The miniſterye is come to this pointe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte generally, that if you will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amin any ones liuing, you ſhall find
<pb facs="tcp:12212:8"/> more, that are worthy to be reproued, then rewarded, and more to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, then well liked, ſuche is our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection. We are called to an high office, an office of great dignity. Wee are God his miniſters, and nothing appeareth leſie in vs then Godlines. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes</hi> called to bring Gods people from the tyranny of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> left kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping his ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epe, and followed his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, wee are called to guide Gods people from darknes of ignorance, to the lighte of knowledge, from the bondage of ſin, to the liberty of grace, and yet we ſtand in our old ſtate, we forſake not the world, we change not our courſe, wee alter not our life, wee ſhould be light, and we are darkneſſe, we ſhould be miniſters, and wee are become Lords, wee ſhoulde feede oure flocks, and we famiſh them Finally, we ſhould be preachers, and wee are dumb doggs, and tongue tied. God, I beſeech him, loaſe them, that we may worthily ſet foorth his prayſe, which now with ſilence we obſcure, that our light of preaching may ſo ſhine before
<pb facs="tcp:12212:9"/> men, that they ſee our good workes, with the chaunge and renuing of our liues, and ſo they may glorifie our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is in heauen. Wee haue here alſo another leſſon, both notable and very fruitfull: that al they, which are ſo called of God, are moſt obiect to all kindes of temptation, and they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, which are moſte in ſauour with God. For our Sauiour Chriſte before his baptiſm, was not ſo temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Deuill, as he was after, when hee was ſeperated from the worlde, and conſecrated wholly to the miniſterie of God, and erecution of his office, then the ſubtle Sophiſter, and craftie tempter, began to ſtir the coales. He perceiued Chriſt went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſet forth the glory of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which he moſt ſpitefully enuied from the begin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing, and ſo diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſought wayes and meanes, as hee could moſt peruerſly to let and hinder him. Neither did the malitious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent at the beginning tempt any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature, but that which was made af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the likenes and ſimilitude of God.
<pb facs="tcp:12212:9"/> hoping to deface Gods glory, if he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> might or could deforme that creature, which was of all Creatures vnder Heauen, moſte lyke vnto GOD. Euen ſo here, when he perceiued that Chriſt was by the mouth of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be his onely beloued ſonne, in whom his anger againſt ſin, and indignation againſt ſinners, was ful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly quieted and appeaſed: and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt now ſhould take vpon him to worke the will of his father, ſo as ſhoulde be for his fathers glory, like as hee did before with our firſte parentes, ſo he doth now: that is, he laboureth firſt to bring Chriſte to that point, that hee ſhould not beleeue the voyce of God, which had ſayde: <hi>This is my beloued ſonne:</hi> Secondarily, from the true vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of Gods worde, and to bring him to manifeſt idolatrie at the length, contrary to Gods worde. In like danger of temptation are all they, which be either in high authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as was <hi>Dauid, Zedechias, Moſes,</hi> when the people grudged, or els that be greatly in Gods fauour, as the good
<pb facs="tcp:12212:10"/> man <hi>Iob,</hi> and <hi>Tobias,</hi> which was made blind by the Deuill, and the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the deſart, which were ſtir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red of the Deuill to murmure againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and God, and diuers other which haue beene ſuddenly tempted. The Deuill is crafty, and tempteth not all men one way, becauſe all men are not in loue with one thing, and becauſe he will not ſeeme to be as he is, <hi>He changeth himſelfe into an Angell</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>of light,</hi> as <hi>S. Paule</hi> ſayeth <hi>to the intent he may deceiue.</hi> Therefore he tempted <hi>Eue</hi> one way, and the iuſt and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man <hi>Iob</hi> an other. He tempteth Chriſt here one way, and afterwarde his Apoſtles an other. As Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe beareth witneſſe, ſaying: <hi>Simon the Deuill hath deſired you, to ſift you as</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>it were wheat, but I haue praiell for thee, that thy faith fayle not.</hi> And as we ſee by experience, Cities, Townes, or Caſtles, ſet on high hilles or moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, are moſt obiect to all ſtormie tempeſtes, and violence of weather: In the very like manner are they which are called to high dignitie,
<pb facs="tcp:12212:10"/> great authoritie, and worthy offices, moſt in danger of temptation and the aſſaultes of the Deuill. The golden writer <hi>Chriſostome,</hi> in his fourth Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melie<note place="margin">Chriſoft. hom. 4 in Eſay. 6.</note> vppon theſe wordes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>I ſay, vidi dominum. &amp;c.</hi> hath a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſimilitude to confirme this to bee true. As the maner is in ſhips, they which haue an emptie ſhip feare not Pyrates of the ſea, which ſeeke not to bruiſe or breake an emptie or voyde ſhip: but they which haue their ſhips full fraughted with wares and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of merchandiſes ſtand in fear of robbers, which ſeeke thither where gould, ſiluer, and precious ſtones are to be had: Euen ſo the deuill doth not eaſily purſue a ſinner, but rather a good and godly man, who hath much riches. Let that man therfore, yee all men take heed, which eyther are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in high authoritie, or haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued gyftes and Talents at God his hand, of the wicked tempter, that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about to robbe and ſpoyle man, of ſuch heauenly treaſures as God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth vpon him. And here alſo, they
<pb facs="tcp:12212:11"/> that haue grace may learne, that the lyfe of a Chriſtian man, is neyther playe, nor paſtime, neither daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing nor daliance, neither fleſhly, nor licentious liberty: but a laborious and dangerous warfare, a charie and circumſpect keeping of a Godlie and innocent life. Let carnall Goſpellers perſwade themſelues they haue God by the toe, or in their boſeme neuer ſo much: if they be not in a ward of this warfare to fight againſt the Deuill, the victorie of Chriſt ſhall not auaile them, but ouerthrow them with their captaine, whoſe luſts and deſires they follow. <hi>For all they, which will liue god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>in Christ Ieſu, must ſuffer perſecution,</hi> which is not without great tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wherefore <hi>Bainabas</hi> and <hi>Paule</hi> after they had preached at <hi>Derbe,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Lystra, leone,</hi> and <hi>Antioch,</hi> making ſtrong the Diſciples, and comforting them, with exhortations to continue in the faith, <hi>becauſe that</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>thorow many tribulations, wee must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the kingdome of God.</hi> Many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples might be brought to prooue,
<pb facs="tcp:12212:11"/> that they are moſt in danger of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, which are moſt in authoritie: But becauſe the time will not ſuffer me to be long, I will come to the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelist,</hi> which ſayeth: <hi>Christ was led into the deſart to be tempted of the Deui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> As theſe wordes declare the fact to be of God his prouidence, and no fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate or vnlucky chance or happening vnto Chriſt: ſo it is an admonition for vs all, to enterpriſe and take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in hand, that is of great weight and importaunce, vnleſſe we be ledde there vnto by God his holy ſpirite, or commaunded by his worde to doe the ſame. For Chriſt him ſelfe was led of the ſpirit to be tempted of the Deuill, in the deſart. Not to faſt, but to bee tempted, and although hee faſted, it was but an accidentarie or incident thing, beſides the principall matter, which was, to be te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted. This exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would be diligently noted for two cauſes. One is, that it is a particuler example, but once done of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt in al his life: The other is. that the holy Ghoſt led him to worke
<pb facs="tcp:12212:12"/> the ſame miracle. And therefore it ought not to be an example of imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto vs, as many men woulde haue it, but a wounderfull myracle once wrought of one man, and no more. Here I may note by the way, rather then ſpeake of by leaſure, how ſmall conſideration men haue vſed heretofore, which haue inioyned all them, that woulde take vpon them to be miniſters of Gods worde, a ſingle lyfe without marriage, no reſpect of circumſtances had, eyther of him that taketh the yoke and bond vpon him, or of God, in whoſe power it is, to giue the gift of chaſtitie as it pleaſeth him. For conſider theſe two thinges, faſting, and chaſtitie, what affinitie they haue, and whether they be of like force or difficultie to bee obſerued of man, or no. As God hath made man to liue: ſo he hath appointed him an ordinarie way to liue, vnleſſe he haue a ſpecial prerogatiue and miraculous helpe of God, as had <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> by the ſpace of fourty dayes. And ſo in like caſe, God hath made man to mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiply
<pb facs="tcp:12212:12"/> &amp; increaſe the worlde, to which ordinaunce with obſeruation of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtaunces neceſſary to the ſame, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man is bonden, ſaue they which haue a ſpeciall prerogatiue of God, to lyue in fleſhe without fleſhe, which is an Angels nature, and not mans, as <hi>S. Hierome</hi> ſayth. They may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med therefore, that thus wryth and wreſt the ſcriptures, to ſatiſfie their licentious affections and wicked hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, to condemne that in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, which in God his word, is both lawfull and laudable. Little they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde the leading of the holy Ghoſt, without whoſe motion they ſhoulde enterpriſe nothing, ſeeing our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, was led of the holy Ghoſt into the deſart, to be tempted of the Deuill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <note place="margin">The Tex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> And when he had fasted fourty dayes, and fourty nights, he was hungry.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ius</hi> ſuppoſeth forty nights to be added of the <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>angefiſt,</hi> for a difference betweene the <hi>Lewes</hi> faſtes, and his. For the maner of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12212:13"/> was, to faſt all the day, and to eate at ntght: But Chriſt did not ſo, for the ſpace of forty dayes, and forty nights, in all which tyme he hungred not. Two ſuch examples of admiration rather then imitation, we haue in the olde Teſtament: the one is of the holy Prophet or God <hi>Moſes,</hi> who beeing<note place="margin">Exod. 24.</note> commanded of God to aſcend &amp; come vp, into the mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> to fetch the tables of the commandements which he ſhoulde afterwardes deliuer to his people, faſted al the tyme that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the Mount, which was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty daies, and forty nights, and al that ſpace neither eate nor darcke, as is written in the booke of <hi>Exodus.</hi> The other is, of the Prophet <hi>Elias,</hi> who fleeing from the wicked Queene <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabell</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. King. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Achabs</hi> wyfe, and reſting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnder a iuniper tree being wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his life and wiſhing to die, was ſed by an Angell ſent to him from God, with a cake baken on the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes and a cup of water. After which refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion or nouriſhment, he walked four<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty dayes and fourty nightes a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12212:13"/> ſtrength therof, vnto <hi>Horeb.</hi> the mount of God. Our ſauiour Chriſt therfore, whom theſe two Prophetes did prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, when he ſhoulde begin to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and preach the Goſpell, departed from the company and ſociety of man into the deſart, where he faſted fourty dayes, and fourty nightes, not excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the meaſure which <hi>Moſes;</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> had before obſerued, leaſt hee might ſeeme to paſſe the boundes of mans nature, and by a myracle make it ſeeme incredible that hee was true man, whom afterwards the experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of hunger did teſtify to be ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. So much then as Chriſt is better then <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo much is grace better then the law, becauſe that as Saint <hi>Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> fayth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>The lawe was giuen by Moſes, but</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>grace and truth came by Ieſus Christ.</hi> For notwithſtanding the lawe was written with God his own hand, and pronounced with his mouth, yet as S<note place="margin">Heb. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth: <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ad but a ſhadow of good things to come, &amp; not the things to their owne faſhion.</hi> Wherefore if <hi>Moſes</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted forty dayes twice, before he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:12212:14"/> and miniſtred the law, it was no derogation to Chriſte his dignity, to faſt forty dayes, before he beganne to preach the Goſpell, which is the truth of the ſhadows that went before. And in like ſort, <hi>Elias</hi> as it followeth in the 3 of <hi>Kings</hi> the 19. Chapter: when he went a farre iourney, and ſhoulde bring a great matter to paſſe, that is, anoint, or as we in <hi>England</hi> tearm it, Crowne two Kinges, and conſecrate one Prophet, faſted forty dayes, and forty nightes. Which vndoubtedlye was a great Myracle in him, both to labour a long iourney, and alſo to faſt all the iourneys ſpace. Chriſt therfore to ſhew himſelfe nothing inferiour to either of them, faſted forty dayes and forty nightes. Vppon which faſt, and the faſtes of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> becauſe the Church hath of long time, taken occaſion to ground and inſtitute this faſt of Lent, which at this preſent we obſerue: I entend by Gods grace and your Chriſtian patience, by iuſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this text, and by opportunitye of the time and place, to ſpeake ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:12212:14"/> of this our Lent Faſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, ſhewing the true definition of Faſt, and that this Faſt of Lent, obſerued nowe by vs, can neither be grounded on the old, nor the new Teſtaments: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondarily, how it was firſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Church: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and then, how farr our ſuperſtitious vſing of it, differeth from the firſt inſtitution.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Faſt is not, as wee commonly call and vſe it, forbearing of fleſh in Lent, or vpon Fridayes, Ember dayes, and ſuch other, for ſo no learned man did euer take it: but it is an abſtinence from all kinde of meate and drinks, wherewith mans body is nouriſhed, and a continence from all vaine wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton pleaſures, wherwith mans mind may be infected. This generall faſt hath bene diuided into two kinds: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> one Corporall, when wee abſtaine from bodily meates, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the other Spirituall; when wee refrayne from all kinde of vice and ſinne. Some, take Faſt to be a due ſatiſfaction of all mans ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: as if a man ſinne with his eyes, <hi>to turns them away, that they regard no</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12212:15"/> 
                  <hi>vanities,</hi> as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayth, <hi>or elſe to pluck</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>them out</hi> (as Chriſt biddeth) <hi>when they offend vs.</hi> And likewiſe in all other partes and ſenſes of mans bodye. Howbeit this is more ſpirituall then the other, that I haue recited. For in the other are included three kindes of faſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> One is, abſtinence from meate and drinke to keepe vnder the body, that the fleſh be not fierce againſt the ſpir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te: and that is voluntary, vſed of euery man as he ſeeth occaſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out compulſion. Such is their faſt, though not of like force, that for their health abſtaine to diſgeſt euil ſurſets, and ſuperfluous meat. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> An other kind is of neceſſitie, not enioyned man by any lawe, but by God: As in time of Dearth, Famine, and ſcarſitie of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall. This faſt as it is not volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily vſed of man, ſo it is not obſerued without great grudging and murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring againſte God which ſendeth it, as a plague for our ſinne. And this faſt they that ly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in bondes and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, lacking neceſſary meat &amp; drinke, doe ſuſteine and abyde. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The thirde
<pb facs="tcp:12212:15"/> kinde of faſt, is a generall Faſt of all men, and women. Which the Iewes often vſed, eſpeciallye in the time of great plagues, warrs and ſuch extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, abſteining from meate and drinke in aſhes and ſackcloth al the daye long, thereby to humble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues before God. Yet none of theſe Faſts are like that heauenlye faſt of <hi>Christ, Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Elias.</hi> For their faſts were aboue theſe faſtes in all points. Wherefore touching the firſt part of faſt, which we obſerue all this Lent, it is moſt true that I ſayd before: It could not be grounded on the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. For notwithſtanding that <hi>Moſes</hi> faſted fourty dayes twiſe, and <hi>Elias</hi> once, yet becauſe their faſtes were miraculous, we neither ought nor can ſincerely follow them. And beſides, we may by as good reaſon fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low <hi>Moſes</hi> in all other miracles that hee wrought, as in this: And ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Elias.</hi> For if they had beene workes as well of imitation, as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, no doubt the <hi>Iewes</hi> which were ſo ſtudious to inuent new tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,
<pb facs="tcp:12212:16"/> would haue made this one of their cheifeſt. But they knew verie well that as theſe faſtes were myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles: ſo they were in no caſe of man to be imitated But in examine it more nearely. <hi>Moſes</hi> faſted fourty daies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">Exod. 24.</note> he receiued the commandements of almighty God, contayned in the two Tables: which when hee had throwne downe and broken, as hee came from the hill, for the diſpleaſure he conceiued againſt <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the people: he was commanded to aſcend<note place="margin">Exod. 34.</note> the ſecond time to receiue the law at Gods hand, and to bring and teach it the people. And ſo he did. Wherevpon the <hi>Iewes</hi> in remembrance of the law giuen them by <hi>Moſes,</hi> keepe a ſolemn feaſt euery year, in the ſixt day of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ninth moneth: that is, as they count their moneth on the ſixt day of May. It is one of their ſolemne feaſtes cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Penticost,</hi> their Whitſonday, which was the fiftieth day after they were come forth of <hi>Egipt.</hi> They ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a ſolemne Feaſt, but no faſting for it. In the tenth moneth the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth
<pb facs="tcp:12212:16"/> day: they obſerue and keepe one Faſting day for a remembraunce of the tables which <hi>Moſes</hi> brake, when<note place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> he hearde that the people committed Idolatrie. Seeing therefore the <hi>Iewes</hi> yearely celebrate a memory of the law giuen, and alſo faſt one day in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of breaking the tables: It is not to be thought contrary, but they woulde willingly haue obſerued Lent as we do, if it had bin but mans exerciſe, and no miracle. They obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued diuers dayes for faſte and abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, as the third day of the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, which is <hi>September,</hi> which is talled the faſt of <hi>Gedalia.</hi> In the fourth moneth they faſt in remembraunce of the ſiege that <hi>Nabuchodon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>zer</hi> layd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the citie <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> In the ſixt month on the thirtenth day they kept the faſt of <hi>Ester</hi> and <hi>Mardocheus.</hi> And although that <hi>Ester</hi> commaunded all<note place="margin">Heſt. 4.</note> the <hi>Iewes</hi> to faſt three dayes and thrée nights to obtayne Gods fauour, that they might find fauour and grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the king <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> and ſo eſcape the bloudy handes of <hi>Haman,</hi> which
<pb facs="tcp:12212:17"/> intended their deathes all in one day: yet in remembraunce of the ſame, the <hi>Iewes</hi> obſerued but one day yearely, and that was the thirteenth day of the ſixt moneth. And this faſt was one of the longeſt faſtes that I haue obſeruod in the old Teſtament: except we ſhould take it, that the <hi>Niniuites.</hi> faſted all the tyme that was graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them for repentaunce, which was fourty dayes. But that they faſted ſo<note place="margin">Ionas. 3.</note> long, it is incredible, becauſe man, beaſt, and all kind of cattell faſted, or els ſurely the popiſhe church woulde not haue fayled to draw that into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, when <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> woulde not ſerue their purpoſe. Here I haue rehearſed the greateſt part of the <hi>Iewes</hi> faſting dayes, which were or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily and yearely vſed of them, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in remembraunce of preſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie from their enmies, or ſome great calamitie that befell them vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſuch dayes as they kept faſted. But our <hi>Lent</hi> faſt can bee grounded on none of all theſe, becauſe that in the fore ſayd monethes there was but
<pb facs="tcp:12212:17"/> one day faſted. And as for their extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinaries, which they kept by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of plague, Battell, Famine, and ſuche like greate calamities, as they were not certainly obſerued vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any daye: So wee can not ſtabliſh oure Lent after them, becauſe their dayes and moneths are variable. And if we ſhould ſo doe, yet our faſt agreeth not with theirs, in ſo much as they put no ſuch difference betweene fiſhe and fleſhe, as we do, although indeed they had certaine kindes of fleſhe prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their law. And as for the faſt which the Secte of the <hi>Phariſes</hi> in Chriſts time obſerued twiſe a weeke, it were fooliſh to obiect it for any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of our Lent. For why ſhold we approoue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which the <hi>Phariſes</hi> did, who (as both <hi>Ioſephus</hi> &amp; <hi>Epiphanius</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes) were an hereticall ſect? And as they ſuperſticiouſly inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it. ſo they moſt wickedly abuſe it: As we may learne by the wordes of our Sauiour, when hee warneth his diſciples to take héed of their faſtings, prayers, and almes deedes. Here then
<pb facs="tcp:12212:18"/> is no authority in the old Teſtament to vphold our old accuſtomed Lent.</p>
               <p>Now to come to the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we ſhal find neither reaſon nor authoritie there, which can make for the obſeruation of the ſame, vnleſſe we ground it vpon this faſt of Chriſt. And that cannot be: For Chriſte his faſt as it was much beyond mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo naturally it ought not to bee practiſed or atempted of any man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not an example imitatiue, but miraculous. But the Papiſtes which woulde gladly beare out the matter with the authoritie of this place, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge a ſaying of <hi>S. Gregorie, That euery action of Christ is our instruction.</hi> The ſaying of it ſelfe is moſte true: but their concluſion gathered of it is moſt falſe: that we muſt doe al things that he did, becauſe they are our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. For this is as good a reaſon as theirs is: euery action of Chriſt is our i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtruction, but to heale the lame, to make the blind ſée, the dumb ſpeak: the deafe heare, are actions of Chriſt. Therefore we muſt make the blind,
<pb facs="tcp:12212:18"/> ſee, the dumbe, ſpeake &amp;c. Who is ſo ignorantly blinde, that cannot ſee the the abſurditie and fooliſhneſſe of this reaſon: And what prerogatiue or pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eminence ſhould Chriſt haue, I pray you, if eyther we ought or could do the like? To preſume to doe them were great derogation to his glory, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly commeth of the pride of the Deuill, that woulde ſeeme to be like God. I maruell much that they can ſpye that in Scripture which men of profound knowledge could not ſee.<note place="margin">In Mat. ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 47.</note> For <hi>Chriſostome</hi> plainlye affirmeth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> our ſauiour Chriſt ſaith not his faſt is to bee imitated, wheras he might propoſe his Faſt of Forty dayes, but he ſayth, <hi>Learn of me, for I am me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke &amp; humble in heart.</hi> In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new teſtament we haue plentifully declared vnto vs both in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Euangeliſts &amp; in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles of the apoſtles, wherin we ought to follow Chriſt, and yet we are in no place willed to follow his forty dayes faſt. Truth it is, that the goſpell both exhorteth and commandeth vs to faſt but it appointeth vs no certayne day
<pb facs="tcp:12212:19"/> as: thou ſhalt faſt euery Fryday and Saterday, but not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sunday, neyther doth it appoint vs to faſt more from fleſh then fiſh, God his worde, makes no difference betweene the one kind, and the other. For our ſauiour Chriſt when hee willeth vs to faſt, ſaythe on this wiſe: <hi>when thou fastest, anoint thy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>head, and waſh thy face.</hi> By which words he would we ſhould auoide hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, and not appear ſuperſtitious vnto the world, but that we ſhoulde ſo faſt, <hi>that our Father which ſeeth in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete, may reward vs openlye.</hi> Hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth no mention heere at all, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his fourtye dayes, or of anye kind of meate which we ſhoulde ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from: Yea, we may ſee by his communication with the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſes,</hi> what his will was concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eating of meates. For he ſayth, <hi>That which goeth into the mouth of man</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>defileth not the man, but that which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the hearte, that defileth the man: as euill thoughts, murther, adultrie, fornication, theft, falſe witnes, and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> Wherefore <hi>Cyrill</hi> vppon theſe
<pb facs="tcp:12212:19"/> wordes of Chriſt, in S. <hi>Iohn</hi> his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,<note place="margin">Cyrill vpon Iohn. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>By this all men shall know that yee are my Diſciples, if yee loue one an other,</hi> For as much as the perfection of all vertue conſiſteth in loue, let no man thinke hee can attaine to anye great thing by abſtinence or faſting, or by lying on the grounde, or by any vertuous exerciſes els, vnleſſe he loue his brother: for he is not carried to the marke, but an other way. Such is Chriſt his commaundement concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faſt, not that he requireth no ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence from meates at all. For as <hi>S. Luke</hi> teſtifteth he giueth this war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to his diſciples, and it may well ſerue as a caueat for vs: <hi>Take heed to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>your ſelues, least at any time your heartes be ouercharged with ſurfeting and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, and cares of this life, and least that day come on you ſuddenly, which ſhal catch as in a ſnare, al them that dwel vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, watch therfore &amp; pray alwais, that yee may auoyd all theſe euilles.</hi> If <hi>Lent</hi> had beene ſo neceſſary for mans ſaluation, as the Biſhoppes decrees make it, which ſay it is a deadly and
<pb facs="tcp:12212:20"/> damnable ſinne to break it, certainly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euangeliſts wold not haue omitted it, no more then they did other things which they haue left vs in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings to follow. Chriſt in no place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the new teſtament ſayth, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me, let him faſt once in the yeare forty dais, but he ſaith: <hi>He that wil fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>me, let him deny him ſelfe, &amp; take vp his croſſe dayly, and follow me.</hi> If any man wil obiect that a Chriſtian man his faſt, is a part of his croſſe: then I wil anſwere, that his croſſe muſt bee daily taken, and ſo by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> means a faſt of forty dayes will not ſerue, but hee muſt faſt euery daye, all the dayes of his life. If any of you require a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or playner viewe of the matter, looke vpon our Sauiour his ſermons made to his Diſciples in the mount. Wherein he ſheweth the happye and bleſſed ſtate of all Chriſtian and faith ful beléeuers, and yet maketh no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch happineſſe or beatitude, as is pretended our Lent or our abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from fleſhe bringeth with it. <hi>Bleſſed are the poore in Spirite,</hi> (ſaythe<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12212:20"/> Chriſt) <hi>they that mourne, the meeke, they that hunger and thirst for righteouſnes, the merciful, the poore in hart, the peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, they that ſuffer perſecution for righteouſnes ſake. &amp;c.</hi> In all which hee ſaith not, they are bleſſed that faſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes in Lent and abſtayne from fleſh: nay, there is not one worde that can bring a man to any thought or i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination of it, except hee ſurmiſe that S. <hi>Luke</hi> make for him, becauſe he ſayth ſimply, <hi>Bleſſed are they that hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>for they ſhall be ſatiſfied.</hi> And ſo make this reaſon: faſt makes a man hungry: but the hungry are bleſſed. Therfore they that faſt are more bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, For ful reſolution of which argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, let <hi>S. Luke</hi> be conferred with <hi>S. Mathew</hi> and <hi>S, Luke</hi> his meaning wil eaſily appear. For <hi>S. Mathew</hi> his place is a perfit expoſition of it, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which <hi>S. Luke</hi> toucheth briefly, <hi>S. Mathew</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth more at large. The one ſaith: <hi>Bleſsed are they that hunger now.</hi> The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith: <hi>Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirst for righteouſnes, for they ſhall be ſatisfied,</hi> And this bleſſing onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayneth
<pb facs="tcp:12212:21"/> to the elect of God, not to euery <hi>Turke,</hi> or <hi>Iew,</hi> or wicked perſon when he is hungry. But do you think that the Apoſtles were either ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, or ſo negligent, that neither in their acts nor in their Epiſtles they would make mention of it? if it had béen ſo neceſſary to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as many make it. The apoſtles, at what time certain falſ brethren went from <hi>Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> to <hi>Antioch,</hi> perſwading y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Gentiles</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> were conuerted to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith, to be circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed &amp; liue after <hi>Moſes</hi> law, aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled them ſelues together to conſult what was beſt to be done in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. In which conſultation they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to ſend <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> with other of the brethren to <hi>Antioch</hi> with letters concerning their mind, which was not to burthen them with the importable yoke of <hi>Moſes</hi> law, but to<note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> wil them to abſtain fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> things offred vp to images, &amp; bloud, &amp; that that is ſtrangled, and from fornication. Now if our faſt from fleſh had beene neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the Chriſtians, it had beene an eaſie matter for the Apoſtles to
<pb facs="tcp:12212:21"/> haue ſet it downe in their Epiſtles or letters, that as they ſhoulde at all times forbeare the eating of thoſe meates that were offered to Idols, from bloud. &amp;c. So they ſhould once in a yeare faſt fourty dayes from fleſhe together, as in time of <hi>Lent.</hi> But the Apoſtles neuer dreamed of any ſuch ſuperſtition in faſting, much leſſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to wryte of it. For they knew miracles were not to be followed. And although they preſcribe faſting, yet no ſuch faſting: but as from fleſhe, ſo from all kinde of meates, as by their owne faſt doth appeare. For <hi>S. Paule</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 27.</note> himſelf with many that were in ſhip with him, faſted not one day or two, but many, euen fourteene without meat or drinke: and he wryteth of his faſting to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> but of anie ſuch faſt as this is, he ſpeaketh in no place. Wherfore it can not be approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the euangeliſts. For if we wil ground it vppon Chriſt his faſt, then muſt oures neceſſarily agree with Chriſtes in ſome point, which in no point agrée any more then an Egge
<pb facs="tcp:12212:22"/> and an Diſter, neither in tyme, place, nor in any other circumſtance. As by collation of the one with the other, will appeare manifeſtly. For Chriſt was baptiſed the ſixt of <hi>Ianuarie,</hi> and in the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th day (as ſome me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> write) he was led of the holy Ghoſt into the deſart, (or as the Euangeliſt ſayth) <hi>by and by, or immediately after his baptiſm:</hi> and then he began his faſt, which he continued for the ſpace of forty dayes and forty nights, vnto the fifteenth or ſixtenth day of <hi>Februarie.</hi> About what time for the moſt part our <hi>Lent</hi> begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, ſometime before, and ſometime after: As this yeare it beginneth iuſt about the time that Chriſte his faſt ended. Chriſt faſted immediatly after his Baptiſme, when hee was thirtie yeares old: we faſt after our baptiſme indéed, but not before we be ten years old. Chriſt faſted but once fourty dais in thirtie three yeares: But we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to Faſt fourty dayes euerye yeare, taking more vpon vs in one yeare, then wee are ſcarce able to perfourme in all our lyfe. Chriſte
<pb facs="tcp:12212:22"/> faſted fourty dayes from all meates: and we abſtain from no meats in the forty dayes, but onely from fleſh, and think we follow Chriſt wel to. Chriſt in fourty daies was not an hungred: And ere we haue faſted fourty hours, our gorge gapeth for meate, and our bellies thinke our throates be cut. In what point then doth our faſt agree w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt his faſt? do you perceue any one thing agreeing? Yet this is mans preſumption to take that moſt vpon him, that he is leaſt able to do. What reaſons are in ſcripture in the olde or new Teſtamentes, you may by theſe few perceiue. For I haue alleaged the moſt manifeſt places that make for the faſt of fourty dayes, as <hi>Moſes, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias,</hi> and our Sauiour Chriſt. Now therefore ſeeing it can not be groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on ſcripture, I will come to the next part before propoſed: and that is how it was vſed of the fathers in the Primitiue Church, and how ours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth with the ſame.</p>
               <p>Concerning this part, to ſpeake the truethe: the obſeruation of <hi>Lent</hi> is
<pb facs="tcp:12212:23"/> no new thing, not a yeſterdayes bird, or inuented of late yeares: but it hath beene vſed euen from the beginning of the Primatiue Church, not then commaunded vnder any paine to be obſerued of all men, but of mans vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie accord without precept. And yet they that firſt obſerued it, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not to follow Chriſt his faſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was euerie mans deuotion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like. For it was with them, as it is in euery congregation: ſome are more feruent in Prayer then other ſome, ſome are more ready to faſt then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſome more charitable towardes the poore, and more ready to releiue their brethren, then other. All which and ſuch like exerciſes were not then, nor are not now to be enioyned vpon penalties, but are freely to bee left to mans conſcience to do them as his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie will ſuffer him. For as a man is not commanded by God his worde to giue this day more then that: So he is not commanded to faſt one day more then an other, but to doe both a like, as occaſion ſhall ſerue, and hee
<pb facs="tcp:12212:23"/> ſhall be able to perfourme them. And becauſe ſome be poore, and haue more need to receiue then beſtowe, more need to take almes then giue almes, &amp; ſome be troubled with infirmities &amp; diſeaſes, &amp; haue more need of meat to ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, then of abſtinence to humble them therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt in the ſcripture prouideth wel for them, and exhort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th them to pray, not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing them anie certaine ſpeciall time, but at all times, and in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Wherby we may gather, how al theſe are commaunded, or not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded but left to the conſcience of<note place="margin">Hiſt. trip. lib. 9 cap. 38.</note> the doers. Thus at the beginning, ſome men better diſpoſed then others, to ſhew forth a good example of their religion and mortification, began to faſt fourtye dayes once in a yeare. Whoſe example mooued many, that longed to haue the report of religious and godly men, on the ſame faſhion, though not with like deuotion, to faſt fourty dayes alſo. For hipocrites can ſhew as faier a face ſometimes as the godly in deed, and to the worlde they
<pb facs="tcp:12212:24"/> ſeeme more glorious oftentimes, that counterfait the workes of good men, then the ſaintes of God themſelues. Well, at length the matter grewe to this iſſu, and the number of them that vſed this Faſt did ſo multiply, that al they which either were not able to do the like, or not ſo diſpoſed, were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſkant good Chriſtians, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they followed not the common example, and ſo to anoyd the ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous note of vndeuout perſons, rather then of a ready &amp; willing mind, gaue their priuy conſentes to confirme this example. All men thus conſenting, ſome for religion and Godlines ſake, ſome of hypocriſie, ſome to auoid ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ther lacked nothing but laws to ratefie and eſtabliſh this common con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent. And thoſe, the vndiſcreet and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>godly Byſhops not long after conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, rather to get goods, then to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote godlines, and ſet foorth the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God. For without regard or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons, they clogged and fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered men with their leaden ſawes, whoſe conſciences they ought rather
<pb facs="tcp:12212:24"/> to haue diſburthened by Gods word, and to haue left it at liberty, as it was before. We reade in <hi>Euſebius</hi> that the<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 5. cap. 24.</note> obſeruation of Lent was left free for euery man to faſt, or not to faſt, and that it was not generally exerciſed of all men after one ſort. For hee allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth <hi>Ireneus</hi> his wordes to confirme his minde. And the wordes be theſe. <hi>There is a diſputation touching the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner or kinde of fasting. Some men ſuppoſe that the Fast of Lent ſhould be obſerued but for one daie, other ſome two daies, Some more daies, and many fourtie daies accoumpting all the houres both of daie and night for a daie, which variety of the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſeruation of Lent, had not it beginning now first in our time, but longe before vs, of them (I think) which did not ſimplie obſerue at the beginning what was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded them, but fell either by negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence or by fooliſh ignoraunce, into an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther custome. And notwithstanding all theſe, though they vary among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the obſeruation of Lent, yet they haue beene alwayes at quietnes, and now are at peace with vs, neither doth the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie
<pb facs="tcp:12212:25"/> of their fast breake the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our fayth.</hi> Whereby you may vnderſtande, that at the beginning there was no commandement giuen to bind men to forty dayes faſt, ſéeing ſome faſted but one daye, ſome two dayes, ſome more, and ſome forty, and yet (ſaith he) they were all quiet and at peace, in this variety of faſt. I fear me, if we ſhould vary &amp; differ ſo much in the obſeruation of our Lent, (ſuch an opinion of it is fixed in the heartes of the ignoraunt) it would breed ſuch diſcention, that we ſhould rather fall by the eares about it, then keep peace and charitie. But the vſe was godly, where no man was compelled to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from fleſhe, which loued not fiſhe. This teſtimony writeth <hi>Irene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> vnto <hi>Victorius</hi> the biſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi> You may reade alſo in the tripartite hiſtory, that in the faſting dayes one man obſerued one thing, an other, an other thing, For the <hi>Romans</hi> faſt thrée wéekes before Eaſter, beſides the ſab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day, and the Sonday. The <hi>Illy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> and all <hi>Grece,</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12212:25"/> faſt ſixe weekes, which time they call Lent. Some beginne their faſt ſeuen weekes before Eaſter, and ſome faſt but onely three wéekes. Which vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie declareth, that at the beginning men were not compelled, but left to their owne choice, either to faſt or no. For vntill <hi>Gregorius</hi> time, the people were not commanded this exerciſe of faſting, but were onely perſwaded by the exhortations of the Biſhops. And <hi>Euſebius</hi> affirmeth, that <hi>Apollonius</hi> an<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib 5. cap. 18.</note> eccleſiaſticall wryter, reprooued <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus</hi> an heretique amongeſt other things, for making lawes for faſting. And in the decrees the fourth diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we reade that <hi>Teleſphorus</hi> a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> made lawes concerning the Lent, and put a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the faſt of the Clergie, and of the Laitie. For he commaunded that the Clergy ſhould faſt from <hi>Quinqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſima</hi> vntill Eaſter, which is ſeuen weekes, and that the Laitie ſhoulde faſt but ſixe weekes. Which thing to be ſo, <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his booke of ſermons confirmeth, ſaying as it is in the
<pb facs="tcp:12212:26"/> ſame diſtinction: <hi>Quadrageſima</hi> hath ſixe weekes, to which <hi>Teleſphorus</hi> the Biſhoppe added the ſeuenth, and all this time they call Lent. Thus by theſe writers you haue hearde, how Lent was vſed in the Primatiue Church. Now it followeth, that I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, how it came vnto vs as it is, and how we agree with the firſt vſe of it.</p>
               <p>Before <hi>Gregorius Magnus</hi> came to the Popedome, there were no ſtraite laws made to bind man to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious obſeruation of Lent. But in his daies and ſince, the moſt part of groſe ſuperſticio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath crept into the church: and he for his part, as he was very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and diligent to inuent and ſet vp new ceremonies, ſo hee was verie buſie alſo in making lawes for their continuaunce. Amongſt which, hee made a law for the eſtabliſhing of our faſt of fourtie dayes. And becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Scripture woulde not ſit his mouth, nor ſerue his purpoſe directly; he went wickedly about to prooue it by probabilitie, alleadging this place
<pb facs="tcp:12212:26"/> of ſcripture, <hi>Thou ſhalt lay out the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>of all maner of fruits, that come forth of thy field yeare by yeare.</hi> Out of which words, he hath violently wreſted and wrong this inuention: That becauſe fourty dayes he the tenth parte of a yeare, and we be commaunded to lay out the tithes or tenthes of our yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fruites, therefore we ought dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to faſt them, and in no caſe, (except infirmities hinder vs) to breake them, but onely on ſundayes. For ſaith he, from the firſt ſunday of Lent vntill Eaſter, there be ſix wéeks which containe fortie two dayes. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which if you take ſixe ſundayes then there are thirtie ſix daies remayning, which are the tenth part of thre hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred three ſcore and fiue dayes, which make the whole yeare. Now becauſe that thirtie ſix dayes doe not fully an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to Chriſt his faſt, they deuiſed amongſt them to adde the foure daies going before, to make vp the iuſte number of fourty. Wherein they put a monſtrous greate miſtery, and ſaye they faſt fourty dayes for diuers cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.
<pb facs="tcp:12212:27"/> One cauſe is, that they might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and be ſory, for al that they haue tranſgreſſed in the four Euangeliſts, and in the tenne commaundements. For tenne and foure multiplyed one with the other, maketh forty. Which reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what force it hath to perſwade men to bind them ſelues to faſt four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie dayes. I truſt you perceiue well inough, and I know the meaneſt and ſimpleſt of you is able to anſwere it, otherwiſe I would labour more in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening the ſubtletie of it. The ſecond cauſe is, that they ought to conforme them ſelues to their heade Chriſte, which faſted fourty dayes. Vnto this reaſon I haue anſwered ſufficiently before, and I hope you are both ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and confirmed therein. For this number which they ſay, hath a miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie<note place="margin">Gen. 7. Deut. 8.</note> in it. They alleadge many places of ſcripture: as in <hi>Noah</hi> his time, all fleſhe without the Arke was conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in fourty dayes: and God fed the children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> in the deſart with <hi>Man,</hi> fourty yeares: and was in his mothers wombe fourty weekes: He
<pb facs="tcp:12212:27"/> preached fourty monethes: he lay in his graue forty houres, and ſuch like. What hidden miſteries theſe num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers carry in them, and how much and how aptly they make for this purpoſe, I leaue to your owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The drift of this my talke is, to prooue vnto you, that the faſt of Lent is not, nor hath not beene ſo frée ſince <hi>Gregories</hi> time, as it was before. For hee made it ſo ſtraightly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that not onely fleſhe, Egges, and ſuch meates were forbidden, but alſo all maner of delicates, as may bee ſeene by many places of the decrees.<note place="margin">Diſtin. 5. de con.</note> Now that their faſt might ſeeme like the faſt that the Primitiue Church obſerued: for a while they eate no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before night. But when ſuch belly God Papiſtes, that coulde not faſt as others had done before them, bare rule, they inuented a pretie pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie if God would haue permitted it, and ſuffered them to haue brought it to paſſe: But becauſe they coulde not do what they woulde, they did what they could: I meane when they could
<pb facs="tcp:12212:28"/> not remooue night, they altered the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onted time of Euerning prayer, and ſayde it before noone, that then they might more lawfully cramme their paunches, and not prolong their faſt vnto the Euening, as was accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: Or els without all doubt, the ſame faſt ſhould haue continued vnto our time. Such were their deluſions to make men thinke and beléeue that their faſt was grounded vppon Gods worde in Scripture. And thus haue they beguiled the ſimple in weightier matters, and which touch more neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the foundation of our faith. Now that you perceiue my meaning in theſe aforeſayd caſes: that is, that our faſt of Lent is neither grounded on the olde nor new Teſtamentes, and that we differ from the Primitiue Church, making neceſſity of it, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they made libertie: It ſhall not be needfull for me to trauaile any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the matter. Yet becauſe I haue ſayde many thinges, which vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly denie our Lent faſt to be groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on God his worde, and all that
<pb facs="tcp:12212:28"/> haue heard me be not like affectioned, amongſt whom perchaunce ſome wil rather ſpeake the worſt, then the beſt of thoſe thinges that they fancie not. I muſt needes ſpeake ſomething in mine owne defence, againſt euill and flaunderous reports, which els would be bruited of this my ſermon. I mean not (beloued) to reuoke any thing hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſpoken. For all that I haue ſaid is ſo true, that I durſt be bould to publiſhe it, to the view of the world, and to maintaine it againſt all them that be aduerſaries vnto it. If ye will not credit me in theſe thinges, reade the ancient and learned Doctor ſaint <hi>Augustine</hi> in his Epiſtles: Where he ſaith, <hi>The examples of ſaints (meaning</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. 86. ad Caſul. con. vrb.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes and Elias) are not of force to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the fast of any one day, much leſſe the fast of the Sabboth day.</hi> For of that dayes faſt, he writeth purpoſedly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one <hi>Vrbicus.</hi> And concerning the new Teſtament, he ſaith: <hi>I peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or calling to mind, that which is in the writinges of the Euangeliſtes, or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, yea and in the whole instrument.
<pb facs="tcp:12212:29"/> which we call the new Testament, I ſee or perceiue that fast is commaunded: But vpon what dayes we ought to fast, and vpon what we ought not to fast, I finde it not decided, eyther by any commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lorde, or of the Apostles.</hi> This writeth the holy Doctor in that place. What ſhall we ſay then for the vſe or continuaunce of it? Verily I wil ſay for my diſcharge, as the ſayd Doctor ſayth in the latter end of that Epiſtle, <hi>That if we wil neyther ſlaunder nor be ſlaundered, let vs follow the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome of the Church where we are.</hi> If it be not contrary to Gods worde, and yet the thing vſed be commendable. For although in his Epiſtle to <hi>Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arius</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nnati. 119.</note> he ſaye, that Lent hath his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of <hi>Moſes, Elias, and Christ:</hi> Yet might he better haue aunſweared by a rule that he giueth after in the ſame Epiſtle: <hi>That thoſe thinges which are not agaynst our fayth, nor godly and good maners, and haue ſomthing to the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a godlyer lyfe: whereſoeuer we ſee them instituted, or know them to bee iustituted, we ſhould not only not improue,
<pb facs="tcp:12212:29"/> but with prayſe and imitation followe them, if the infirmitie of ſome doe not ſo hinder, that greater harme follow.</hi> In like maner ſay I, touching this faſt of Lent, that becauſe it being vſed as the Fathers haue vſed it, is not contrary to any Article of our faith, nor godly conuerſation, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it haue no expreſſe ground in ſcripture, may be well and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable vſed, ſo long as the King and the Counſaile for the profite and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of this Realme, pretending no holineſſe or religion in it, think it expedient. And in this reſpect, where you faſt fourty dayes, for my part I would rather wiſhe you to faſt fourty daies more then one leſſe, it beeing ſo neceſſary ſor our common wealth, as it is. And therefore haue I thus much ſpoken, to make it knowne vnto you, that it is not any commaundement of God, but a politique and ciuill lawe made for the wealth of the Realme: and is with like reuerence and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to be obſerued, as other lawes made for our maintenaunce and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation.
<pb facs="tcp:12212:30"/> Of which obedience to the King and his lawes, I would gladly intreat if time would ſuffer me. But becauſe it paſſeth very faſt away, I will returne to my text.</p>
               <p>It followeth, <hi>That when Christ had fasted fourty dayes and fourty nights, he was afterward hungry.</hi> As it is an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent token, that by his faſt of fourtie dayes and fourty nightes, and not to hunger, there is in him a power farre aboue the nature of man: So in that he hungred, it can not be denied but he was man. And this is a meet place to prooue the humanitie of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, againſt all thoſe heretikes that denied him to bee man. For in that he hungred afterward, he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe to be man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Then came the tempter to him and ſayd, if thou be the Sonne of God, make theſe Stones bread.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE ſubtle craft of the Deuill, is plainely deſcribed in this, that the Euangeliſt calleth him the tempter. For ſo long as fourtie dayes did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue,
<pb facs="tcp:12212:30"/> and Chriſte was not hungry, the Deuill woulde not aduenture to tempt him: But when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourty days were expired, and Chriſt waxed hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, he tooke the occaſion and began to flatter. And wheras before he doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to preuail, hearing God cal Chriſt his dearely beloued ſonne: Yet now perceiuing Chriſt to be hungry, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be ſomewhat more confident, and yet doubted too. For theſe two pointes ſeemed very abſurd to him, that he ſhoulde both be the ſonne of God, and be hungry. And therefore here he beginneth to be buſie, and by reaſon of his hunger to tempt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him. Beginning with our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, as he had don with <hi>Eue,</hi> when he<note place="margin">Gen 3.</note> perceiued ſhe was deſirous of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple forbidden. For when he perceiued her appetite prouoked, he perſwaded her to diſtruſt and diſobey Gods word which threatned they ſhoulde die the death, <hi>whenſoeuer they eate of the apple forbidden.</hi> Theſe ſubtle waies he v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with all afflicted conſciences and troubled mindes, when they once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb facs="tcp:12212:31"/> to faint or doubt of God his promiſes. In the deſart when the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael began to lack ſuch ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance, as they had in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> hee moued them to grudge and murmure both againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and God. In time of dearth and famine, which is a ſcourge of God, hee endeuoureth to make man thinke and beleeue that God hath forgotten him, or elſe that God doth not regard him: otherwiſe, he beareth them in hande, that God according to his promiſe would bleſſe all them which keepe his will and commandements, with corne, cattell, and all other things moſt plentifully: and not ſuffer them to lack in time of neede. And where he ſeeth the good afflicted with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bad, he cauſeth them to grudge and murmure againſt God in ſuch time of viſitation. But if ye require examples of Sathans ſuggeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, you may eaſily remember, how of late days, in this realme he procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vs to murmure, grudge, &amp; with open mouth to blaſpheme God in the time of our ſcarſcitie and pouerty,
<pb facs="tcp:12212:31"/> ſent amongeſt vs for the triall of our fayth, and perfection. And becauſe we haue not ſuch aboundance of victuals and other thinges wherewith this realme hath heretofore beene moſte plentifully bleſſed: the deuill moueth vs not to impute it vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true cauſe, which is, our abhominable liuing: but vnto a falſe fained cauſe, which is, the extirpation of hypocriſie and ſuperſtition, the rooting out of all I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, I meane, to ſpeake plainlie, the ſuppreſſion and ouerthrow of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beys, Monaſteries, and all other falſe religious and rebellious houſes. For thus ſayth the vngodly: we had neuer good world, ſince the abbeys, and ſuch other houſes were pulled down, with ſuche blaſphemous wordes againſt God, as it grieues me to repeat. The deuill perceiuing vs more bent to ſerue our bellie then God, and that we lacke part of thoſe things which wee inioyed abundantlie before, ſo tempts our gready guttes, impatient of any lack, that he maketh vs to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pheme God, and to ſlander his word.
<pb facs="tcp:12212:32"/> Hee mooueth vs not to conſider how much better it is to ſerue the liuing Lorde in the deſart with a little, then to be captiue vnder the proud hand of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and to continue in bondage and ſlauery by the fleſhe pots of <hi>Egipt,</hi> But if we know how much libertie from ſinne, is to bee preferred before the tyrannie of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or the deuil, we woulde not grudge, but be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for our deliueraunce. When Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beis ſtood, &amp; Monaſteries, or houſes of religion, or miſrule rather, floriſhed, we were vnder <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the prince of darkeneſſe, we were Captiues to the ſeruitude of ſinne, and bondſlaues to ignoraunce: with all the wealth that we had: and now beeing ſet free and at liberty from the ſame, ſhal we grudge at our God, becauſe Sathan tempteth vs? He taketh an occaſion of vs, or els he would not be ſo buſie. He tempted <hi>Eue,</hi> when he ſaw her deligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted<note place="margin">Ciril. lib. 9. cap. 16. in Ioh.</note> with the apple: And amongſt vs hee ſeeth neceſſitie, and that we are not content with it, and therefore would haue vs murmure and grudge.
<pb facs="tcp:12212:32"/> In like ſort dealt he with Chriſt, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king occaſion of his hunger, ſaying: <hi>If thou be the Sonne of God, &amp;c.</hi> As though he would haue ſayd to Chriſt: <q rend="margQuotes">Perchance thou thinkeſt thy ſelfe to bee the Sonne of God, becauſe that when thou waſt Baptiſed of <hi>Ihon,</hi> thou heardſt a voice ſaie: <hi>This is my dearely beloued ſonne, in whom I am well pleaſed.</hi> Yet thou mayeſt be deceiued: For who can thinke or beleeue that God will ſuffer his ſonne ſo to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of all comfort, to liue in the deſart, to be in company with beaſts, and to lacke mans helpe and ſuccour in time of neede? Now thou art hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grie, what wilt thou eat? Here is no bread: go to, if thou be Gods ſonne as thou perſuadeſt thy ſelfe, by the voice which thou heardeſt, linger no longer in hope, prouide for thy ſelfe ſeeing God doth not. Here is nothing to eat, and thou art fair from the City: here be ſtones, change them into bread, it is an eaſie thing for thee to do, being Gods ſon. Thinkeſt thou God loueth thee, that letteth thee hunger ſo long?
<pb facs="tcp:12212:33"/> Thou mighteſt quickly perceiue, that thou art deceiued being ſo ſore hung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: and yet God ſends thee nothing to ſatiſfie thy deſire.</q> Thus the deuell laboured not ſo much to tempt Chriſt by bidding him ſatiſfie his hunger, as to make him diſcredite God his word &amp; that he was not Gods beloued, as before he had hard. Likewiſe perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded he our forefather not to beleeue Gods word, which was a farre grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matter then the eating of the forbidden fruite. Hee knoweth right well, that the promiſes of God are ſet foorth for the ſaluation of man, and that our health dependeth onely ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon. And therefore hee ſtudieth to make vs let ſlip our hold, and the hope that wee haue therein. Let vs then watch and be diligent, leaſt our fayth grounded on the infallible trueth of Gods worde, by his craft be weakned and peruerted. For if he preuaile ſo much with vs, as to ſeduce vs from the veritie of Gods holy worde, &amp; to yeeld our ſelues ouer as ſlaues to his wicked temptations: Lord what ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:12212:33"/> become of vs? will not horrour be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore our eyes continually to trouble and terrifie vs? Shall we not liue in darkneſſe and in the ſhadow of death, and ſtand euen at the brim of the pit of deſperation? O then (dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) what need had we to be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, and to take heed of ſathans ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions. For he goeth about continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally either by him ſelfe or his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, euen like a roaring Lion, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king whom he may deuour, whom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in faith, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> biddeth you.<note place="margin">Pet. 5.</note> For though he pretend neuer ſo faire a countenance, and ſeeme to giue you neuer ſo good councel, though he coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfait the ſimilitude of an Angell of light, yet he will be ſathan and a lier ſtill, and will ſeeke your confuſion. <hi>Reſist him therefore stedfast in faith.</hi> The wicked members of Sathan tempted our ſauiour Chriſt, when he hanged on the croſſe for mans rebe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and reuiled the mighty God with contumelious wordes: <hi>If he be the Sonne of God, let him come downe, and we will beleeue him: And if God will haue him, let him ſaue him,</hi> with many
<pb facs="tcp:12212:34"/> like wordes of deteſtable wickednes, and horrible blaſphemie. And thus he daylie tempteth the Godly, to bring them to infidelity. Againſt the which I beſeech you marke Chriſt his aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, it will be much to our conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation and comfort. <hi>It is written: Man liueth not by breade onely, but by euerie ward that proceedeth out of the mouth of God.</hi> Which teſtimonie or aunſwere is taken out of the olde Teſtament, where <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake vnto <hi>Iſraell</hi> on this wiſe. <hi>Thou ſhalt remember all the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>way, which the Lord thy God hath br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght thee, this fourty yeares in the deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rt, that he might chasten thee and prooue thee, to know what was in thine heart, whether thou wouldest keepe his commandements or no. Therefore hee humbled thee and made thee hungry, and fedde thee with Man, which neither thou nor thy fathers knew of, to make thee know that man must not liue by breade onely, but by eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry word that proceedeth out of the mouth of the Lord must a man liue.</hi> The euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt following the ſeuentie inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters addeth, <hi>euery worde</hi> (which is not in the <hi>Ebrew</hi> text) to ſignifie the
<pb facs="tcp:12212:34"/> vertue and power of God his worde, to be of as great efficacie and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to nouriſh man, as other creatures appointed for the ſame. For as by his word all creatures and things were made and created: ſo, by and from the ſame worde haue all creatures their vertue and ſtrength for mans food and nouriſhment. And therefore our ſauiour Chriſt bringeth ſcripture to confirme, that albeit cuſtomably and ordinarily man liueth by his meate and drinke, yet God both hath, and can ſhewe his power other wayes. He fed the children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, not with accuſtomed meates as at other times, but with a ſtraunge maner of bread, and ſuch as none of them knew. Séeing then, God ſo mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uailouſly fedd his people in time paſt in the deſart, and that not for fourtie dayes, but for fourtie yeares ſpace, ſhould he not be thought able to féede his dearely beloued ſonne in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart now alſo, vnleſſe hee tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiat ſtones into bread? If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to feede man fourty yeares with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out breade, is hee not able to feed his
<pb facs="tcp:12212:35"/> dearely beloued ſonne fourty dayes without bread? Nay (bearly beloued) God is not bound to meanes, but ſometimes he deal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th with meanes, ſometimes without, and ſometimes againſt all meanes, and as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Lorde ſo come all thinges to paſſe. For the Lorde God is omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. What needeth bread then, when God can ſend him heauenly food from aboue? <hi>Man liueth not by breade onely, but by euery worde that proceedeth out of the mouth of the Lorde must man lyue.</hi> Our ſauiour thus with ſcripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeth the temptation of the deuil, that thereby we may learne to do the ſame, without the conſent either of cuſtome or councell. For this was the Deuill his intent, to make Chriſte thinke that becauſe man lyueth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monlie by bread and drinke, therfore Chriſt coulde not poſſibly liue any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waies. But he was far deceiued: for Chriſte eaſely conuinced him. I coulde wiſhe that all they, which ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are tempted, or aſked a queſtion, woulde vſe to aunſwere by ſcripture yea or no, and not be ſo much addic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:12212:35"/> and ſworne to cuſtomes and coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cels. For they conſider not what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie they doe to the maieſtie of God, that preferre mans doctrine before the holy ſcripture. Chriſt might haue aunſwered otherwiſe if it had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, but he aunſweared by ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to teach vs to adhere and ſticke to ſcripture, as to a ſure ancker in all queſtions propoſed. For hee might haue ſayd, why tempteſt thou me? As though I coulde not lyue without breade. Can not I that giue life to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and am life it ſelfe, liue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bread, and prouide ſufficiently for my ſelfe without thy councell? Thou haſt no charge ouer me, and therefore care not for me: for I can care for my ſelfe? Thus might our ſauiour haue cut him off, if hee had thought it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, and haue rebuked him ſharp lie: but he replyed with the ſcripture, and that with ſuch gentleneſſe, that the deuill was more ready and more bould to tempt him now, then before. For it followeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Then the Deuil tooke him vp into the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:12212:36"/> Citie, and ſet him on a pinacle of the Temple<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THE deuill perceiuing that his former temptation preuailed not, inuenteth an other. For when hee coulde not bring Chriſt to infidelitie before, now he trveth him with vaine glory. It is wonderfull to ſee the fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and ſhyfts that ſathan vſeth, and yet neuer any without ſome probali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For it may ſeeme that he grounds his deuiſes vpon the practiſes of ſuch m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, as thinking they bee in Gods fauour, to winne praiſe and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, dare run headlong into daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers on their owne accord without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny neceſſity at all. This conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he may ſeeme to haue had, when he take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h and ſetteth our Sauiour on the pinacle of the temple at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> reaſoning with him ſelfe (as it were) on this maner: <q rend="margQuotes">For as much as my firſt purpoſe is fruſtrate, I wil at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the matter an other way. I wil try whether vaine glory will allure him to ſhew ſome miracle at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> where the multitude that looke &amp; behold him, may magnifie and ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:12212:36"/> gloriouſly of him. There is no man in this deſart to looke vppon him, but at <hi>Ieruſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>em</hi> there is greate preaſe of people, and therefore I will lead him thither, and ſet him on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pinacle, and will him, if he be deſirous of fame or glory, to throw him ſelfe downe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long in the ſight of all the people, that he may be had in reputation amongſt them, and perchaunce be made their king &amp; cheife gouernour. But to bring this poll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cie to ſome effect, he repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſame words that he had vſed before: <hi>If thou be the ſonne of God. &amp;c.</hi> Seeing thou ſtickeſt ſo much to the words that thou heardeſt at thy bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and that thou truſteſt ſo ſurely in Gods prouidence, that thou wilt not ſeeke for thy ſelfe in extreame po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty and hunger, caring for nothing to refreſhe thy feeble body withall: it were good for thee, if thou wouldeſt be accounted as thou takeſt vpon thee to be, to ſhew ſome ſtraunge feat to the people, to ſettle and perſwade them in the truth of the matter. And therefore if thou wouldeſt follow mine aduiſe, I woulde giue thee councell to goe to
<pb facs="tcp:12212:37"/> 
                     <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that famous and populous City, where to confirme vnto all the people which ſhall behold thee with a miracle, that thou art Gods ſon, the ſauiour of the world, the Meſſias that they haue long looked for, thou ſhalt caſt down thy ſelfe headlong from the pinacle where I will ſet thee. Thou needeſt not to doubt or feare any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the peril is foreſeene, and a reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy prepared. For God, whoſe ſonns thou thinkſt thou art, hath giuen his Aungels charge ouer thee, <hi>They ſhall take thee in their hands, least at any time thou ſhouldest dash thy foote against a stone.</hi>
                  </q> Is not this a goodly pretenſed councell, to ſet a man in the maſt of vainglory with ſuch coloured words? What a ſtrong perſwaſion was this? Tell me beloued, what Orator or counſailor of them all, can handle his matter more cunningly? Surely it is ſo baited with ſweete and entiſing wordes, that it is impoſſible for any, but the ſonne and ſaints of God, and ſuch as God miraculouſly deliuereth, to auoid him, and eſcape his tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For infinite no doubt is the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:12212:37"/> of them, that both in time paſt, and at this preſent, Sathan hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunted and enflamed with vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory: and I beſeeche God there bee none amongeſt vs. Amen. Here you may note with me the deuill his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertnes in ſcripture, who diſdaining to take ſo ſudden a repulſe at Chriſts hand, alleageth one place of ſcripture for an other. The place that he citeth is in <hi>Dauids</hi> pſalmes, where the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.</note> ſetting forth the happy ſtate and felicitie of them, that are vnder Gods protection and prouidence, among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comfortable verſes, hath theſe two, which ſathan in this place infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth againſt Chriſte, ſaying as it is written: <hi>He shal giue his angels charge ouer thee for to keepe thee in all thy ways They shal be are thee in their hands, that thou dash not thy foote against a stone.</hi> Which words declare, in what aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance they liue that put their whole truſt in Gods defence, and what fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly care the lord hath ouer his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miteth them, as kings and great men do their heirs to faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full nourſes, vnto the protection of
<pb facs="tcp:12212:38"/> his angels, that they fal not into dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. But the deuill both depraueth &amp; abuſeth the true ſenſe &amp; meaning of this place. For one part he omitteth which is in the Prophet, and all the reſt he applieth to falſe promiſes, and wicked perſwaſions. For notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the faithfull and elect of God be kept of angels in all their waies, yet are they not beſide or againſt their waies. The waies of man you know are common and ordinary: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were a madd point for a man, becauſe aungels are his ouerſeers, to take vpon him to ſwim ouer the ſea, when he may ſail ouer by ſhip, or for Chriſt to haue caſt him ſelfe headlong from the pinacle, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he might come downe by ſome other ordinary way. For this had bin to tempt God his fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, &amp; to ſuſpect him as it were, that he would not be as good as his word. Take heed therfore how ye truſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than whoſoeuer ye are, yea though he bring ſcripture with him. For though he apply the ſcripture neuer ſo truely (which he ſeldom doth) yet al tendeth to your vtter deſtruction. Hence learn
<pb facs="tcp:12212:38"/> likewiſe, to out your whole affiaunce in the prouidence of God, and yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes vſe the ordinary meanes that he hath apointed you. For otherwiſe you ſhew your ſelues not ſo much to truſt in him, as to tempt him, as the deuill did our ſauiour. To reaſon here how the deuill tooke Chriſte, whether bodily or by imagination, as ſome haue don, becauſe it is a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more curious then fruitful, I thinke it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to paſſe it ouer, then to ſearch it out. Let vs for our parts learn herely that the deuil is buſie in tempting all them that be placed in authority. For like as that citie or caſtel that is ſet &amp; builded on the top of an hil, is moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen and obiect to all ſtormie tempeſts and blaſts of weather: ſo they that be aduanced and ſet (as it were) on the pinacle or top of office, honor, or digni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie, are moſt egged on by the deuill to caſt down them ſelues thorow ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, vaine glory, couetouſnes, &amp; ſuch like offences. All of vs trauaile with too much loue of our ſelues, and that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> deuill eſpies well inough, or els hee woulde not be ſo néere our elbowes at
<pb facs="tcp:12212:39"/> all times as he is. But we miniſter him matter to worke on ſtill, which vntill we ceaſe to doe, he will neuer leaue off his temptations. For Gods ſake therefore remember your ſelues betime, and reforme theſe things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, that God may haue his glory, Gods miniſters ioye, and the deuill ſhame by your good conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now let vs heare what aunſwere Chriſte made to this ſcripture alleaged of the deuill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Againe it is written: Thou shalt not tempt the Lord thy God.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BEcauſe the deuil alleaged ſcripture our ſauiour replieth with ſcripture againe: <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Thou shal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> not tempt the Lord thy God.</hi> As though he ſhould ſay: thou perſwadeſt me to caſt my ſelfe downe backward, and to haue no care what I do, <hi>Becauſe God appointeth his angels to keepe me.</hi> I beleeue certainely that the <hi>angels will beare me in their handes, that I hurt not my foot against a stone.</hi> I know that God hath deputed them to kéepe mee, yet will I not follow thy wicked councell, for I haue thy mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at my fingers ends. Thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb facs="tcp:12212:39"/> haue me to tempt God my father as thou madeſt the fathers in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, with miracles notneceſſary. But I know their rewarde, and how they ſped, I wil take héed by their harmes. I am a man, and I wil follow mans waies, and not caſt my ſelfe headlong into daunger where I néed not. Here is a way to come vp, I will come down the ſame way. What néed I to tempt my God, or try whether his an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gels will preſerue me, hauing y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame way to deſcend, that I aſcended? I am forbidden to do it, and euery man els, and therfore I will not. <hi>For it is wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: Thou shalt not tempt the Lorde thy God.</hi>
                  </q> Theſe wordes of our ſauiour are written in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fift book of <hi>Moſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> where,<note place="margin">Deut. 6.</note> after that <hi>Moſes</hi> had giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out the ten commandements to the people, as it is in the chapter next before, and had exhorted them to feare the true God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by renuing his promiſes made to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, &amp; Iacob,</hi> their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, he forbiddeth them idolatrie, and giueth them this charge with all: <hi>Ye shal not tempt the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rde your God, as yee did tempt him in the place of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12212:40"/> Which was, when they came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deſart of ſin, and by the Lords ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment camped at <hi>Rephidim:</hi> wher finding no water to drinke, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to chide with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and aſked him: <hi>Why hast thou brought vs out of Egipt, to kill vs, our children, and our cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell with thirst,</hi> And they tempted the Lord ſaying, <q rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Is the lord among vs, or no?</hi> As if they had ſaid: thou haſt brought vs into this deſart, where nothing ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be found for vs to drinke. We are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thirſty, and more like to pine a way for lack of water, then to liue, vnleſſe we depart, and yet thou makeſt vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde here ſtill. Couldſt not thou haue ſuffered vs to tarry in <hi>Egipt,</hi> where we had plenty both of meat &amp; drinke: but thou muſt leade vs hither, where we want both? We can not thinke, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God is among vs. For if hée were, would he ſuffer vs, (beeing his owne people) to be thus afflicted for lacke of drinke?</q> Thus did they repine &amp; gruge againſt <hi>Moſes:</hi> and therefore he called the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Maſſa</hi> or <hi>Meruba,</hi> the place of temptation or ſtrife. And to this point the deuill bringeth man in his
<pb facs="tcp:12212:40"/> aduerſitie and affliction to think that God is diſpleaſed &amp; angry with him, and that the promiſes of God apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain not vnto him: by that meanes to make him diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aire of him ſelfe, and his own temptations may take place. As though God coulde no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be among them, whom he afflicteth, nor fauour them, whom he viſiteth. <hi>S. Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le</hi> vſing the wordes of <hi>Salomon,</hi> biddeth the<note place="margin">Prou. 3. Heb. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>brewes</hi> be of an other minde: <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe not the chastening of the Lorde, neither faint when thou art rebuked of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im: For whom the lord lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th, he chast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth: and be ſcourgeth euery ſon t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at hee rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> As God then might be and was among them, thogh he puniſhed the Iſraelites with lacke of drinke, ſo that it was vnneceſſary to try it by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miracle: ſo it was vnneed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull for Chriſt to prooue him ſelfe the ſonne of God, or to try whether angels would preſerue him, to caſt him ſelfe downe headlong from the pinacle. For that had been a flat temptation. So y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> you ſée how aptly Chriſte alleadged this place. <hi>Thou sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t tempt the Lord thy God.</hi> Out of which words what l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:12212:41"/> may profitably be gathered. Though I haue partly ſhewed you before: yet marke againe I beſech you, for a good thing can not be tolde too often. We learn how dangerous a thing it is to tempt, &amp; to try God, and to truſt to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary helpes, when ordinary means are apointed for vs. This is a grieuous temptation, and yet vſed too commonly of very many in this our realme of <hi>England.</hi> For there be ſome idle belly God perſons, that becauſe Chriſt biddeth vs not to be careful for our liuing, but to looke on the byrds of the ayre, that liue and labor not, take occaſion to loyter at our dores, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly neglect all honeſt labour, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might liue like other men. But experience prooueth, and we ſee it with our eyes, that ſuch perſons for the moſt part fal to robbing &amp; ſteling, and ſo béeing vnworthy to liue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> will not labour for a due rewarde of their life miſled, are hanged to death. And there be ſome, that becauſe the letter killeth, &amp; knowledge maketh proud, neglect ordinary ſtudy: And becauſe Chriſt when hee ſendeth his diſciples
<pb facs="tcp:12212:41"/> to preach, promiſeth to giue them in the ſame houre what they ſhoulde ſpeake, thinke it not needfull to ſtudy the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. If we ſhoulde looke that the holie Ghoſt ſhould onely giue vs knowledge by a miracle of inſpiration, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temn the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſual meanes, wherby all men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly attaine to knowledge, both in Gods worde, and in all other ſciences, were not this to tempt God as the deuil tempted Chriſt? In vaine then were the tonges, books, interpreters, readers, and all the inſtrumentes that God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. For albeit the ſpirit of God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth euery mans heart before hee can vnderſtand, yet he giueth knowledge to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether with his meanes: As the <hi>Eunuch</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 8.</note> of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> who vnderſtanding not what he read, before God vſed the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>Philip</hi> to inſtruct him, doth moſt plainely declare. And <hi>S. Augustine</hi> in his fourth booke <hi>de doctrina christiana</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de doct Chri. cap. 16</note> ſaith: <hi>That if this reaſon were good, a man shoulde not pray at al, becauſe God knoweth what we haue need of before we pray. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>should the husband man till or ſow his ground, becauſe neither he that planteth nor</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>he that watereth is any thing, but God bat
<pb facs="tcp:12212:42"/> giueth the encreaſe.</hi> But thus you may ſée how ready the wicked and vngodly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies are to tempt God, as ſathan did Chriſt. Againe, in that Chriſt anſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the deuill his allegation of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the ſcripture, we may learne to interpret one place of ſcripture by an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when they ſeme to repugne. But ſurely if the deuil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> had beene ſo ſaucy with Chriſt, as many are in our day<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, which will admit no ſenſe, but ſuch as pleaſeth them: he might haue replyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt, and ſayd: It is no temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of God, to caſt thy ſelfe downe: for God hath charged his angels to keep thee in all thy wayes. So that whether thou goe downe, or caſt thy ſelfe downe, thou ſhalt be ſafe. Thus might the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill haue reaſoned, following the literal ſenſe of the wordes But he was a more gentle diſputer, and not ſo impudent in ſticking to the letter as the Papiſtes of our daies are. He knew by Chriſtes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that he had miſtaken it, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ceaſed to contend any longer about that text, but tryed him an other way, as enſueth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>The D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uil tooke him vp againe vnto an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb facs="tcp:12212:42"/> high mountayne, and shewed him all the kingdomes of the worlde, and the glory of them. &amp;c.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>THis is the third temptation after this Euangeliſt, but after <hi>Luk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> it is<note place="margin">Luk. 4.</note> the ſecond Wherby you may ſee they la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured not ſo much of the order and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as of the matter it ſelfe. They both agree of three temptations, though they vary in the order of them. But the deuill deſirous to bring his purpoſe about, I know not thorow what ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chauing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oile before, is not aſhamed to aſſay the matter againe: And therefore he vſeth a more eaſie way. He willed not Chriſt here to deny God directly, nor to worke any miracle, but he went about to make him in loue with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> world, with welth &amp; riches, wherby many men many times decline from God vnawares. Neither doth the deuill trifle in the matter, but he offereth euen the largeſt and the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt kingdoms of the world, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame him, as he thought the more, hee ſheweth them, and al the glory of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a viſion. Marke the ſubtletie of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. He biddeth not Chriſt fal down and worſhip him on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plaine ground in the
<pb facs="tcp:12212:43"/> deſart, but <hi>he taketh him vp into an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g high moun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aine, and sheweth him all the coastes and kingdomes of the worlde,</hi> in the braueſt and glorieſt maner that he coulde, ſaying: <q rend="margQuotes">Is not this a pleaſant kingdome? Is not this a welthy realm? Is not this a glorious empire? O how happy &amp; fortunate are thoſe rulers, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in ſo high eſtate? What a delicious lyfe might he lead y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> were Lord ouer two or three of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Might not y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> man triumph? Al theſe kingdoms which thou ſeeſt are in my hand to diſpoſe &amp; beſlow where &amp; how I liſt. This I giue to this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and that to an other: but if thou wilt do as I would haue thée, &amp; be ruled by me, I wil ſet thee aboue them all. For it is meet y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the ſon of God ſhould haue larger &amp; grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter kingdomes, then any worldly prince And therefore I am contented to giue thee, not onely al theſe kingdoms which thou ſeeſt, but alſo the power and glory of them. Thou ſhalt not buy them: thou ſhalt pay neither gold nor ſiluer for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I wil aſke but reaſon of thee, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou fal down before me, in token of obedience &amp; homage and worſhip me. I require but little: yet do this, &amp; I will perform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> my
<pb facs="tcp:12212:43"/> promiſe.</q> The world would think this a maruailous te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation: here are as ſwéet words as can be. For who is more bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to his lord, then he that payeth no rents for his lands? Our landlords wil not let out their groundes ſo good cheape. But th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe words as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tempter vſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, are moſt falſe and full of blaſphemous I do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. For though the deuill, the ruler of darknes, be called the prince of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, yet he is not ſo called, as though he had kingdomes or empires at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, (for the land is the lords, &amp; in his hands are the ends of the world) but the deuil is called the prince of the world, becauſe he ruleth &amp; beareth the chiefe ſtrook ouer the children of vnbeleife, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in ſcripture are called the world. So that he lyed falſly, in ſaying all the kingdomes of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> worlde were his, and it was a blaſphemous pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſumptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt God, to motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt Ieſus to fal down &amp; worſhip him. Who as he hath béene a blaſphemer of God &amp; his works fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning: ſo he continueth in theſe our daies, perſwading the worlde no leſſe to fall downe &amp; worſhip him now, then he did heretofore. For I know not how but
<pb facs="tcp:12212:44"/> ſure it is ſo, &amp; my conſcience wil not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to conceale it, Sathan hath taken many of our miniſters, and carried the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp to an exceeding high mountain, and ſhewed them al the ſpiritual liuinges <hi rend="margQuotes">almoſt in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> world, Byſhopricks, Dean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Prehends, Perſonages, and vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages, and hath told them: this is a wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Byſhoprick, this is a rich Deanrie, this is a fat benefice, they are all in my</hi> gift, I am y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> patron of them: fall downe therfore before me &amp; worſhip me, and if one wil not content you, I wil giue you pluralites. Let n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> think theſe things to be forged or ſucked out of mine owne fingers. For writers make mention, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the deuil in déed gaue the Biſhoprick of <hi>Rome</hi> once, &amp; ſince y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time it was neuer good. And is he not ſo able now, thinke you, to giue a poore benefice, as he was then to giue the faiteſt biſhoprick in the world? Let no man be offended with me for ſpeaking y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſéeth to be true. For where theſe miniſters ſhould be preachers, they are tong tied: and that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not without great temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For thus he reaſoneth with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <q rend="margQuotes">ſpeak no more of iuſtification:
<pb facs="tcp:12212:44"/> meddle no more with controuerſies: ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the ſore: let euery man liue as he liſt without reprehenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or admonion &amp; you ſhal lack no liuing.</q> Do you thinke that ſathan hath not thus ſworne many to ſilence? I haue hard of diuers y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> at the beginning haue beene very godly prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers: but after they haue bin once choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vp with many liuinges, they haue had ſuch a bone in their throates, as the deuil wold haue it, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they would ſeldem open their mouth to ſpeake any more. I beſech God giue vs grace to withſtand &amp; auoid this his flattring and ſweet te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Once not long ſince I ſpake aganſt ſuch in a place where I was, &amp; after my ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was ended, it was tolde me, that ſome called me a yong ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſaid it was but a pang of heate. &amp; that I gaped for a liuing: which obtained I woulde be as quiet as other men. I am a yong man ſtill, &amp; I am not ſorry for it, but I thank my God for it, who I truſt will, at his pleaſure, turn both my youth &amp; mine old age to his glory For <hi>S. Paul</hi> hath taught me not to contemne youth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut where they ſayd it was but a pang, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was not true: for I was as circumſpect in it as I
<pb facs="tcp:12212:45"/> could, &amp; I haue now the ſame mind and iudgement y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> I had then, though a little more confirmed by the ſcriptures &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient doctors: and to ſay I gaped for a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, it is vntrue. For I might haue had ſince y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time a rich and worſhipfull liuing, if I would haue taken it: but if to take a benefice ſhould make me tong<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tied, I had rather haue none whilſt I li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Yet what I ſhould do I cannot tel, I will not preſume too much of mine own ſtrength, ſeeing more godly &amp; better learned men ſeduced by the flattery of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> deuil and the world. But as I am now minded, I had rather go on begging fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dore to dore, and liue in extrem pouerty then without diligent preaching to my flock liue neuer ſo magnifice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. I enuy no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s liuing thogh it were thrée times ſo much, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men take vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more then eyther they are able or willing to diſcharge, it is great ſinne, and ſeemes to proceed from ſathan his temptation. For vndoubtedly men take not ſo many benefices now, becauſe they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or mean to diſcharge them: but becauſe one will not ſuffice to maintain them lordly and wealthily, nor to get goods together for
<pb facs="tcp:12212:45"/> many yeares: The goſpel of long time thorow the tyrannie of the Romiſh <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist,</hi> by whom pluralities firſt came, hath béen made a cloak for couetouſnes. But I pray God pull of the cloake, that euery man may appeare in his plaine coat. Of theſe wicked <hi>Mammonites, S.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Amb. de dig. ſ. cer. cap. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his booke <hi>de dignitate ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dot all</hi> ſaith: <hi>Through mony he hath g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tten honour not due vnto him, and hath lost God in his inward man: flesh hath taken the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and the ſoule hath lost her honesty. The flesh being maid, is become mistres ouer the ſoule, and the ſoule which was miastres is made ſeruant to the flesh. Flesh hath rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the people, and the ſoule ſerueth the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: to his flesh he hath gotten a benefice, and loſſe to his ſoule.</hi> What auaileth it ſuch a one to win all the worlds, and to endamage his owne ſoule? I appeale to your conſciences, to which I ſpeake ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to your eares: Do you thinke Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is not combred with many ſuch as <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaketh off? Let no man take my wordes ſo generally as though I ſecluded none fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this company. For I meane onely theſe couetous dumbe dogs, or ſhadowes of miniſters: not the
<pb facs="tcp:12212:46"/> true miniſters them ſelues, or the good paſtors of their flock. Of whom becauſe the number is ſmal, and the harueſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great, let vs deſire the lord daily more and more to encreaſe it, that his people be not ſtarued for lack of food, but ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thened in the faith to the glory of his name. Thus haue yée hearde the third temptation of Sathan, againſt Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Then ſaide Ieſus vnto him, Auoyd ſathan: For it is written, Thou shalt worship the lord thy God, &amp; him only shalt thou ſerue.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>BEfore, when the deuil went about to make Chriſte diſcredite God in his promiſes, Chriſt anſwered him mildly: but now when the deuil wil prefer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe before God, our ſauiour rebuk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th him ſharply, and commandeth him to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid: but with authority of ſcripture, as he did before. To teach vs, that ſcripture ſhould be our ſhield, our defence and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in al temptation. This ſcripture is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the fift booke of <hi>Moſes</hi> called <hi>Deutronomie,</hi> where <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaketh to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deu. 6. &amp; 10</note> 
                  <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> with like words to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: <hi>Thou shalt feare the lord thy G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d, and ſerue him.</hi> By this place our ſauiour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinceth the deuil, &amp; biddeth him auoide.
<pb facs="tcp:12212:46"/> And here, if I had leſure, I might ſpeak of the difference, which the ſchoole men make betweene <hi>latria,</hi> which is the true and liuely worſhip of God, and <hi>dulia,</hi> which is honeſt obedience due to man, not forbidden by this ſcripture Onely it forbiddeth, to giue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward worſhip of the mind, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> appertaineth only to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, vnto any creature beſids. So y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> theſe words of God alleged by our ſauiour, import thus much, that becauſe God had don ſuch maruailous works, I wonderous miracles for the deliuerance of his people out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not only of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Egyptians,</hi> but of al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> world, noſtrength nor power being able to ſtand or preuaile againſt his might: therfore they ought to feare the lord, and ſerue him. As though he ſhould ſay: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I haue ſhewed ſuch power vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">
                     <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raoh</hi> &amp; his hoſt in working wonders for thy ſake, O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> &amp; haue deliuered thee ſo mercifully from all thy miſeries, me thinks I may by right claim thy ſeruice y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt feare me as a lord of magnificent ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth &amp; power, as an omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t God, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> made all things, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt ſerue &amp; worſhip me, as a merciful, long ſuffering God:</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12212:47"/> thou ſhalt praiſe me, inu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ate me, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on me, as thy helper, thy gouernor thy protector: &amp; that only, thou ſhalt ſéek for health, helpe, aid, ſuccour &amp; all of me and beſides me, of none. If God then be the maker of all things, the giuer of all things, the Lorde of all things, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> made heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, earth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea &amp; al that is therin, if he be giuer of life, liberty, health, welth and whatſoeuer, and haue al things vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his hand: did not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil lie falſly, in ſaying al the kingdoms of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> world were his, and at his diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? did not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l work high treaſon againſt Gods maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, by tempting the Lorde of life to fall down before him and worſhip him, &amp; ſo to haue committed beaſtly and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Idolatry? But <hi>auaunt Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an,</hi> ſaith our ſauiour, thy words preuail not, and thy temptations can take no place: for it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Thou ſhalt not tempt the Lord thy God, but him onely shalt thou ſerue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherby briefly you may vnderſtande, what the true worſhip of God is, &amp; how much againſt Gods glory is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of ſaints: wherof, if I had not been tedious to you already, I woulde haue ſpoken more at large. But I wil haſten
<pb facs="tcp:12212:47"/> towards an end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>Then the deuil left him.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>HEre S. <hi>Iames</hi> his ſaying is prooued true: <hi>reſist the deuil &amp; be wil flee from</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iam. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>you.</hi> By which example we may learne, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> though the godly be continually temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and aſſaulted, yet if they ſtande con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, and ſhrink not, they may be ſure of the victory. For, <hi>God is faithful, which wil not ſuffer them to be tempted aboue their</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>strength</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>&amp; is able</hi> (as S. <hi>Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> writeth) <hi>to deliuer the Godly from</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>temptation. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> was tempted, but he ouer came: the Apoſtles were ſundry &amp; many waies tempted, but they triumphed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, The patriarks &amp; Prophets haue be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e many times tempted, but they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fainted. And here you ſée our ſauiour was tempted, but he ouerthrew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuill and vtterly confounded him, euen with a word of his mouth. This hath our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour bene content to do for vs, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe to Satans temptation, to declare vnto vs, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> whilſte we be in this life we are in danger of temptation alſo but yet if we abide it ſtedfaſtly without ſtarting, we ſhal be ſure to win the vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, as he hath done before vs. Let no
<pb facs="tcp:12212:48"/> man therfore either think it ſtrange or be diſmaied if he be tempted. For can y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> members ſpéed better then the head? Or need the members feare their trial, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the head hath ſubdued the tempter? If the head had fayled, there had been ſome cauſe why the members might feare: but ſince it is otherwiſe, who is ſo faint hearted that can doubt of the victory? Wherefore (dearely beloued) ſince it is ſo, that Sathans temptations can not touche vs, if we perſiſt in the faith, nor preuail againſt vs, if like true ſeruants and followers of our Lorde and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt; we reſiſt him by the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Let vs exerciſe our ſelues in the word of the Lord day and night, and let vs not yeeld either at the firſt, ſecond, or third brunt, but let vs tarry the Lordes leaſure, and in the ende we may be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain euen to weary the deuil, and make him faine to forſake vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <epigraph>
                  <q>And behold, the Aungels came and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred vnto him.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>AFter theſe fourty dayes and fourty nights were expired, and ſathan had left him, our ſauiour began to hun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er: and God ſent his aungels to miniſter
<pb facs="tcp:12212:48"/> ſuch thinges as hee lacked, vnto him. This is a i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> table patterne of conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and patience: He grudged at no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtruſied not Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but tooke all patiently that God ſent: And therefore God ſent his angels to comfort and relieue him. And thus may the Children of God perſwade themſelues, that God will prouide for them in all their extreemeties, if they put their truſt in him. He fedde the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> by rauens, and alſo by<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. King. 17. &amp; 19.</note> an angell. He fedde <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lions denne. God neuer forgetteth nor forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them that truſt faithfully in him. For as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith: <hi>I haue beene young,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>and now am olde: yet did I neuer ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e a iust man forſaken, nor his ſeed ſeeking h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s bread.</hi> But a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſe, our faith is ſo weake, and our charitie ſo colde, our patience ſo ſmall, and our ſturdy ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>maches ſo big, that we will rather tempt our God, ſpoile our neigbours, murmure &amp; fight aganſt God, if he once for our trial ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m to lay his heuy hande on vs, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ther to waite on his leaſure, or to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vpon him, for his fauor. But I beſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the O merciful father, ſo to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs againſt
<pb facs="tcp:12212:49"/> our enemy, that we may haue a valiant conqueſt ouer the deuill, and all his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie, and that we may haue the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Angelical company, as here had our Sauiour and redeemer Ieſus Chriſte: to whome with the father and the holy ghoſt be all honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for euer and euer.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12212:49"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
